Karl Ho

NARRATIVE

I am a political scientist working at the intersection of data science and social science. My research interests span both domains of data analytics and political studies, with a regional focus on East Asia. The unifying theme of my research is to use fast growing scientific methods, data-oriented research design and statistical computing to decipher and prescribe social and political problems. Areas of substantive topics include democratization, political economy, public policy and human rights. I pursue both data analytics and data modeling in building public goods, aiming at improving policies, governance and representation.

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE

Associate Professor of Instruction (August, 2019-present)

Clinical Associate Professor (2013-2019)

School of Economic, Political and Policy Sciences, University of Texas at Dallas

Associate Program Head (2017-2018)

Social Data Analytics and Research (SDAR)

School of Economic, Political and Policy Sciences, University of Texas at Dallas

Director of Academic Computing (October 2005 - present)

School of Economic, Political and Policy Sciences, University of Texas at Dallas

EDUCATION

1992-96	University of North Texas	Denton, Texas
Ph.D. Political Science 1990-92	University of North Texas	Denton, Texas
M.S. Political Science 1984-88 Diploma, Journalism	Shue Yan College	Hong Kong

GRANTS

Research Grants Council of Hong Kong project. "Representation, Fairness, and Participation in Hong Kong's Elections: Assessing Public Perceptions Using a Mixed-Mode Design" (with Stan Wong (PI) at at Hong Kong Polytechnic University, King-wah Fu at the University of Hong Kong, and Harold D. Clarke, proposed funding HK\$ 707,341 (~\$ 90,684.74)

Taiwan Ministry of Education, 2018 Taiwan Democracy Symposium fund, awarded \$4,000

Taiwan Studies Program, Illinois State University, 2018 Taiwan Democracy Symposium fund, awarded \$7,000 Taiwan Studies Program, Kennesaw State University, 2018 Taiwan Democracy Symposium fund, awarded \$3,000

Taipei Economic and Cultural Office in Houston, 2018 Taiwan Democracy Symposium fund, awarded \$1,000 Research Grants Council of Hong Kong project. "Social Cleavages, Civic Engagement, and Election Outcomes in Hong Kong: A New Instrument to Measure Public Opinion" (with Stan Wong (PI) at Hong Kong Polytechnic University and Harold D. Clarke, awarded HK\$ 988,996 (~\$126,794.36)

PUBLICATIONS AND PRESENTATIONS

<u>Iournal articles and book chapters</u>

Wong, Stan Hokwui, Karl Ho and Harold D. Clarke (forthcoming) "Mass Production of Individualized Services: Machine Politics in Hong Kong". *Journal of Electoral Studies*.

Ho, Karl, Cal Clark and Alexander C. Tan. (forthcoming) "The New Southbound Policy as a Reorientation of Taiwan's Economic Strategy" in *The Maturation of a Mini-Dragon: Seventy Years of the Republic of China on Taiwan*. Edited by Yao-yuan Yeh and Hans Stockton, Lynne Riener/FirstForum Press

Wong, Stan Hokwui Wong, KC Lee, Karl Ho and Harold D. Clarke (forthcoming) Immigrant Influx and Generational Politics: A Comparative Case Study of Hong Kong and Taiwan. *Electoral Studies*.

Tan, Alex, Cal Clark and Karl Ho. 2018. "Confronting the Costs of its Past Success: Revisiting Taiwan's Post-authoritarian Political and Economic Development." Asian Politics & Policy, 10(3), pp.460-484.

Ho, Karl, Stan Hokwui Wong, Harold D. Clarke and Kuan-chen Lee. 2018. "A Comparative Study of the China Factor in Taiwan and Hong Kong Elections" in Lee, Wei-chin ed. *Taiwan's Political Re-Alignment and Diplomatic Challenges*. Palgrave McMillan.

Tan, Alexander C., Cal Clark and Karl Ho. 2018. Ending Taiwan's Economic Stagnation: The Implications of the Elections of Presidents Tsai and Trump. *Contemporary Chinese Political Economy and Strategic Relations*. Vol.4, No.3, pp.871-899

Lee, Kuan-chen, Wei-feng Tzeng, Karl Ho and Harold D. Clarke. 2017. Against Everything Involving China? Two Types of Sinophobia in Taiwan. *Journal of Asian and African Studies*, p.0021909617744375.

Ho, Karl, Cal Clark, and Alexander C. Tan. 2017. "Politicized to Mobilize? A Longitudinal Study of First Time Voter Turnout in Taiwan, 2004-2016". *Journal of Electoral Studies*. 24(2), pp.97-115.

Tan, Alex and Karl Ho. 2017. "Cross-strait relations and the Taiwan Voter" (with Alex Tan) in *The Taiwan Voter* ed. Christopher Achen and T.Y. Wang. The University of Michigan Press.

Ho, Karl, Dennis Lu-Chung Weng, and Harold D. Clarke. 2015. "Using repeated cross-sectional surveys to study political attitudes and behavior in a new democracy: HAPC models for Taiwan." *Electoral Studies* 39: 256-263.

Ho, Karl, Harold D. Clarke, Li-Khan Chen, and Dennis Lu-Chung Weng. 2013 "Valence politics and electoral choice in a new democracy: The case of Taiwan." *Electoral Studies* 32.3: 476-481.

Elliott, Euel W., Karl Ho, and Jennifer S. Holmes. 2009. "Political science computing: A review of trends in computer evolution and political science research." *Journal of Information Technology & Politics* 6.2: 166-175.

Ho, Karl, and Jimmy Naugher. 2000. "Outliers lie: An illustrative example of identifying outliers and applying robust models." *Multiple Linear Regression Viewpoints* 26.2: 2-6.

Tan, Alexander C., Karl Ho, Kyung-Tae Kang, and Tsung-Chi Yu. 2000. "What if we don't party? Political partisanship in Taiwan and Korea in the 1990s." *Journal of Asian and African Studies* 35.1: 67-84.

Clarke, Harold D., Karl Ho, and Marianne C. Stewart. 2000. "Major's lesser (not minor) effects: prime ministerial approval and governing party support in Britain since 1979." *Electoral Studies* 19.2-3: 255-273.

Karl Ho. 1999. "The Hong Kong Legislative Election in 1998" Electoral Studies. Vol. 18, pp. 438-45.

Poe, Steven C., Dierdre Wendel-Blunt, and Karl Ho. 1997. "Global patterns in the achievement of women's human rights to equality." *Human Rights Quarterly* 19.4: 813-835.

Recent Presentations:

Ho, Karl. 2019. "New Social Media Sampling Strategy: An Exploratory Study using Non-API methods for Social Data Extraction" to be presented at the 2019 meeting of the International Society for Data Science and

- Analytics (ISDSA) to be held in Nanjing University of Posts and Telecommunications, Nanjing, China, July 6-8, 2019
- "Issues Impacts and Vote choice in Taiwan Elections, 2004-2016" (with Cal Clark and Alexander C. Tan) presented at the 2019 Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting, Chicago, April 5-7, 2019
- "Trumping the Economy?" (with Harold D. Clarke and Marianne Stewart) poster presented at the 2019 Texas Methodology Conference at the Rice University, March 22 and 23, 2019.
- "Non-API Based Data Extraction Methods and Social Media Sampling Strategies: An Exploratory Study using Twitter Data on Domestic and Foreign Policy Issues" presented at the 2019 Asia Political Methodology Annual meeting, Doshisha University, Kyoto, Japan, January 5 and 6, 2019.
- "China Factor in New South-bound Policy: A Comparative Study of Malaysia and the Philippines" (with Tim Chen and Kuan-chen Lee) presented at the "Taiwan and the World in Transition: Opportunities and Challenges" Conference held at the Kennesaw State University, November 9-11, 2018
- "Tweet War amid Trade War: Limitations of Twitter messages and Retweets for Public Opinion Research" presented at the 2018 International Conference on E-society Research, National Sun Yat-sen University, Kaohsiung, Taiwan, ROC, September 14-15.
- "Partisan Networks and Sustainability of Party System: A Network Analysis of Political Parties in Taiwan" (with Lauren Ratliff Santoro, Kuan-chen Lee and Tim Chen) presented at the 2018 American Political Science Association Conference Group of Taiwan Studies (CGOTS) Annual Meeting, Boston, MA, 8/30-9/2.
- "Democratic Legitimacy and Political Activism: An Assessment of Student Movements in East Asian Societies" (with Kuan-chen Lee, Judy Chia-yin Wei, Stan Hokwui Wong and Harold D. Clarke) presented at the 2018 Midwest Political Science Association Annual Meeting, Chicago, April 5-8.
- "Democratic Deficit in East Asia? A Comparative Study of Critical Citizenship in Taiwan and Hong Kong" (with Stan Wong, Harold D. Clarke and Kuan-chen Lee) presented at American Association of Chinese Studies annual conference held at the University of South Carolina, Columbia, SC, October 20-22, 2017
- "Democratic Legitimacy in East Asia: A Comparative Study of Civic Engagement in Taiwan and Hong Kong" (with Stan Wong, Harold D. Clarke and Kuan-chen Lee) presented at "Taiwan in a New Era: Democracy, Cross-Strait Security, and International Relations" conference at the Illinois State University, Normal, IL, October 13-15, 2017
- "The Impact of Issues on the 2016 Presidential Election in Taiwan" (With Cal Clark and Alexander C. Tan) presented at the Conference Group of Taiwan Studies (CGOTS), American Political Science Association Annual Meeting, San Francisco, August 31 September 3, 2017
- "What Political Reforms Do Citizens In An Electoral Autocracy Want: Evidence From A Conjoint Analysis" (with Stan Wong and Harold D. Clarke) presented at the International Studies Association Annual Convention in Hong Kong, June 15-17, 2017.
- "The New Southbound Policy as a Reorientation of Taiwan's Economic Strategy" (With Cal Clark and Alexander C. Tan) presented at "The Maturation of a Mini-Dragon: Seventy Years of the Republic of China on Taiwan" conference held at the St. Thomas University in Houston, TX, April 21-22, 2017.
- "A Comparative Study of the China Factor in Taiwan and Hong Kong Elections" presented at the "Taiwan in the Realm of East Asia" conference held at the Wake Forest University, Winston-Salem, Oct. 21-23, 2016
- "Economic Integration and 'Third Force Voters': A Comparative Study of Taiwan and Hong Kong Elections" (with Harold D. Clarke and Stan Hok-wui Wong and Kuan-chen Lee) presented at the Taiwan Election and Democratization Study conferenced held at the National Chengchi University, Taipei, Taiwan ROC, September 30th, 2016.

"Politicized to mobilize? A panel study of first time voter turnout in Taiwan" (with Alexander C. Tan and Cal Clark) presented at the Taiwan Election and Democratization Study conferenced held at the National Chengchi University, Taipei, Taiwan ROC, September 30th, 2016.

"Houses and Herding: Polling Party Support in Britain" (with Harold D. Clarke and Dennis Weng) presented at 3rd Annual Meeting of Asia Political Methodology at Tsinghua University, Beijing, China, January 8-9, 2016.

"Modeling Hidden Dynamics in Big Survey Data: Models of Voter Attitudes in Election Studies" (With Harold D. Clarke) presented at the International Symposium on Grids and Clouds 2016 13-18 March 2016, Academia Sinica, Taipei, Taiwan

"Measuring Sinophobia in Taiwan: Anxiety, Skepticism, and Its Political Impact on 2012 Taiwan Presidential Election" (with Kuan-chen Lee, Harold D. Clarke and Wei-Feng Tzeng, University of North Texas) presented at the Annual Meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association in Chicago, IL, April 7, 2016

"The Hong Kong Election Study: A New Public Opinion Data Project" (with Stan Wong and Harold D. Clarke) presented at the Annual Meeting of the Midwest Political Science Association in Chicago, IL, April 7, 2016.

"Integration, Identities and Democratization: The Case of Hong Kong" (with Harold D. Clarke and Stan Wong) at International Studies Association (ISA) Pacific Annual Meeting, Hong Kong City University, Hong Kong, June 25-27, 2016

"Was 2016 a Realigning Election?" (with Cal Clark and Alex Tan) presented at the Annual Meeting of the American Association for Chinese Studies, Pepperdine University, Los Angeles, October 7-9, 2016.

"Trade Liberalization and Disintegration: A Comparative Study of the China Factor in Taiwan and Hong Kong Elections" (with Stan Wong, Harold D. Clarke and Kuan-chen Lee) presented at the Taiwan in the Realm of East Asia Conference Oct. 21-23, 2016 Wake Forest University, Winston-Salem, NC

"Economic Integration and Elections: A Comparative Study of Taiwan and Hong Kong" (with Stan Wong, Harold D. Clarke and Kuan-chan Lee) presented at the Taiwan Election and Democratization Study conference held at the National Chengchi University, Taipei Taiwan, October 31st -November 1st, 2016.

"Politicized to Mobilize? A Longitudinal Study of First Time Voter Turnout in Taiwan, 2004-2016" (With Cal Clark and Alex Tan) presented at the Taiwan Election and Democratization Study conference held at the National Chengchi University, Taipei Taiwan, October 31st -November 1st, 2016.

TEACHING EXPERIENCE

University of Texas at Dallas

Methods of Data Collection and Production

Data Visualization (for Social Science)

Political Economy of East Asia

Policy and Politics in China

Politics of China

East Asian Politics

Southeast Asia Politics

University of North Texas

PSCI 2300 Study of Politics (1999-2002)

PADM 5530 Advanced Computer Applications in Public Administration (1997)

University of North Texas Health Science Center

PHPM 5740 Biostatistics: Introduction to Statistical Packages (2000)

RECOGNITION

2019	President's Teaching Excellence Award for Graduate/Professional Instruction, University
	of Texas at Dallas (nominee)
2018	Taiwan Fellowship
2014	EPPS Outstanding Teaching Comet Award, University of Texas at Dallas (Mention)
2013	EPPS Outstanding Teaching Comet Award, University of Texas at Dallas (Mention)
2011	EPPS Comet Award, University of Texas at Dallas
1997	Samuel H. Beer Award - Best Dissertation in British Politics Studies, American Political
	Science Association
1996-97	Sam McAlister Best Graduate Student Award, Department of Political Science, University
	of North Texas
1996-97	Finalist, Best Dissertation Award, University of North Texas
1991-92	Outstanding International Graduate Student, University of North Texas
1991-92	International Education Committee Scholarship, University of North Texas

SERVICES

UTD Learning Management System Committee vice chair (2014)

Electoral Studies Editorial Board member

American Journal of Political Science reviewer

Asia and the Pacific Policy Studies reviewer

British Journal of Political Science reviewer

Comparative Political Studies reviewer

Democratization reviewer

International Studies Quarterly reviewer

Political Analysis reviewer

Political Research Quarterly reviewer

International Relations of the Asia-Pacific reviewer

International Studies Perspectives reviewer

Last updated: March, 2019